<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-30T18:00:10+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bimarsha Adhikari</title><subtitle>Portfolio of Bimarsha Adhikari. Computer Science and Mathematics student at NYU Abu Dhabi. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Value of Models: Why Being Wrong Makes Them Right</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/the-value-of-models/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Value of Models: Why Being Wrong Makes Them Right"/><published>2022-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/the-value-of-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/the-value-of-models/"><![CDATA[<p>Modeling is now an integral part of scientific inquiry—the fundamental laws and theories that hold the key to understanding the ‘real’ world would be far less utilized in absence of well-constructed models. But what does <strong>well-constructed</strong> even mean? Is it necessarily a model that captures reality to the finest details? Surely such realistic models would have more to offer when compared to simple models that leave out variables that we know for sure affect the system to some degree?</p> <p>Is a human dummy a good model to represent a real, functioning human being? Or is a pig better than a mere dummy? At least a pig has life to it!</p> <p>I find this question interesting and quite revealing. Consider providing human dummies of various shapes and sizes to a budding fashion designer and he will make the most out of it. On the other hand, let a medical student practice surgery on pigs initially and she might emerge as a capable surgeon in the future. But now let’s swap the models provided to the fashion designer and surgeon. All of a sudden, a dummy model, which seemed so useful to a designer, turns out to be completely worthless for the medical student. Same goes for the designer. All in all, we would witness a humorous fashion disaster and a rather dangerous medical nightmare if the swap happened.</p> <p>What made all the difference here? In this case, it is pretty straightforward to see that the <strong>usefulness of a model depends on what purpose it serves</strong>. A model constructed without having specific objectives in mind is a quickfire recipe for disaster more often than not. Having a clarity of purpose then guides us to deciding what properties of the target system we desire to have in our model and what properties we can leave behind without much harm.</p> <p>All that a fashion designer wants in a human model is the correct body shape, while a surgeon would prefer models that closely reflect the human anatomy and organs, regardless of how the model looks on the outside. A human dummy model can have an outer shape analogous to that of human beings, but also several other features that we do not find in a human body. A similar statement can be made for pigs and other animals. While knowing what features a model and its target system shares is obviously important, it is as important to be clear about what features the model and its system do not share.</p> <h2 id="understanding-analogies-the-building-blocks-of-models">Understanding Analogies: The Building Blocks of Models</h2> <p>The classification of analogies, formulated by <strong>Mary Hesse</strong>, a British philosopher of science, could be helpful in better understanding this idea. Hesse classified analogies as <strong>positive</strong>, <strong>negative</strong> and <strong>neutral</strong> (Hesse).</p> <p>Simply put, <strong>positive analogies</strong> describe the ways in which a system and its model are similar. <strong>Negative analogies</strong> are the ways in which a system and its model are dissimilar. <strong>Neutral analogies</strong> are those which we cannot classify yet due to our limited knowledge, although we know for sure that they must be either positive or negative. This naturally implies that we know the properties of one of the two analogous entities better than the other.</p> <p>In the case of modeling, we draw certain positive analogies between a model and its target system. We also know for sure the negative analogies involved, which educate us about how not to apply the model to any scenario. However, because we understand our model way better than we understand the real-world, we might ask ourselves a question such as this:</p> <p><em>My model shows a property P. Since my model and the target system have a lot of strong positive analogies, could this mean that a property Q, similar/analogous to P, exists in the actual system?</em></p> <p>Just for the sake of an example, assume that we know very well about sound waves, perhaps because it is easier to produce, sample and analyze. We have identified some positive analogies between sound waves and light waves, namely that both kinds of waves have an associated wavelength, frequency and amplitude as observed from their pitch/color and loudness/brightness. However, we have also concluded via experiments that sound waves cannot be polarized while light waves can be polarized. This counts as a negative analogy.</p> <p>Now, we know that sound waves need a material medium for propagation. Assume that we do not yet know if this is true also for light waves. Then, this is an example of a neutral analogy. Today, we know that light waves, unlike sound waves, do not require any material medium for propagation and can travel through vacuum, i.e. we have sorted this neutral analogy as a negative analogy (Choi).</p> <h2 id="the-necessity-of-simplification">The Necessity of Simplification</h2> <p><strong>Simplifications and idealizations</strong> (such as assuming point masses, frictionless surfaces, massless springs), despite being held as negative analogies, are crucial for model building. On the other hand, a model that demonstrates strong positive analogies with its target system is called a more ‘realistic’ model.</p> <p>Humans throughout history have not remained absolutely limited to what they perceive through their five senses—we have constantly tried to model entities beyond our senses in some way. Otherwise, Dalton, Thompson, Rutherford and Bohr would not have proposed their models of what an atom is. While some might have given models that are more faithful to our experiments and observations, they all have essentially drawn analogies to objects we readily observe, like balls and watermelons (and their seeds), and abstract mathematical objects like points, circles and spheres (The History of the Atom).</p> <p>Now, an important question here is—<strong>how realistic can models get?</strong></p> <h2 id="models-vs-simulations-different-tools-for-different-jobs">Models vs Simulations: Different Tools for Different Jobs</h2> <p>Truth be told, it is not the aim of a mathematical model, in general, to replicate exactly a real-world situation by fitting in as much detail as possible. In a sense, it is rather the opposite—<strong>a good model should be as simple and general as possible</strong>. Complicating the model by crowding every little feature about the phenomenon we know of might make the model more realistic, but not necessarily better at what they are supposed to do.</p> <p>Well, there are certain models that try to make use of every information at its disposal to give a more realistic picture of the real-world phenomenon—we call them <strong>simulations</strong>. However, the utility of simulations differs greatly from that of other models. Simulations are mostly used in cases where we wish to understand the workings of a very particular system. As a result, simulations do not offer much help when it comes to generalizing the result in a broader context.</p> <p>For example: in order to decide a suitable design for a skyscraper that needs to meet the specifications as requested in some island in Abu Dhabi that experiences high heat and wind speeds, simulations are the perfect tool. However, we may not be able to generalize the simulation to this very particular situation easily to the construction of buildings in general. On the other hand, there can be some fundamental and general ideas relevant to all sorts of construction which can be expressed in the form of models.</p> <h2 id="platos-cave-our-eternal-modeling-predicament">Plato’s Cave: Our Eternal Modeling Predicament</h2> <p>This is a particularly striking question that has remained for a very long time, not just in the scientific community but also among philosophers. <strong>Plato</strong>, one of the founders of Western philosophy, strongly believed that what we experience in the real world through our senses is just a pale, shadowy imitation of the true reality, <strong>‘the realm of Ideas’</strong>, as he put it.</p> <p>In his famous <strong>allegory of the cave</strong>, Plato hypothesized a group of prisoners who were confined within a cave with no awareness that an external world even existed. They can only see the shadows cast from the external world, which for them is the true reality. However, one day, a prisoner managed to escape the cave and experience the external world: the trees, birds, humans, houses and so on. He then realized that what he experienced as reality inside the cave was far from being true (Whelan).</p> <p>Unfortunately for us though, <strong>there is no escape from the cave we live in</strong>. Having said so, it would be foolish of us to assume that what we experience is the purest form of reality. What should we do in such a situation then? Should we simply give up on our quest of trying to explain and understand reality in its truest form? Surely not!</p> <p>Modeling is our way as prisoners to try and replicate the shadows that are being casted from the outside with whatever resource we have. We have gotten progressively better and better at this, no doubt. But being able to reproduce shadows fairly accurately is not to mean that the objects we use and the object that is actually casting the shadow we aim to reproduce are the same.</p> <p>For instance, if I cast a shadow using an iPhone and my friend produces a nearly identical shadow, but using a Samsung phone of the same screen size, could one logically claim that the two phones must be the same just because the shadows they produce look the same? Surely, such a conclusion would be far from true.</p> <p>The delusion is pretty obvious in this case, but what some often fail to realize is that claiming to understand the true essence of reality through the use of models and theories is just as delusional. In my view, not just models, but there cannot exist any single entity that can objectively explain true reality in totality, its beauty, harmony and chaos. Of course, I am not referring to unfalsifiable theories but things whose correctness we can deduce through experiments, observations or other means. Thus, I am not hopeful of a grand unified theory of science in the future.</p> <h2 id="why-being-wrong-makes-models-right">Why Being Wrong Makes Models Right</h2> <p>Having said so, I am in no way undermining the immense value of models. In my view, knowing what not to expect from a model and how not to use it is crucial to take full advantage of their capabilities, whether it is explanatory, predictive or both. <strong>Models are useful for the same reason why they are false: they simplify things a lot and this is what gives them strength</strong>.</p> <p>Without simplifying things, models lose their explanatory power simply because of their failure to establish causal relationships among various interacting parts/variables of a system. Choosing the right variables to consider is not a matter of mere guesswork but a thoughtful process. When there are fewer moving parts to a system, we are in a better position to see what effect a particular variable has on the system.</p> <p>In this regard, even a poor model can be useful as it helps us assess how our models behave when certain variables are left out compared to models where those variables are included. After all, how likely is it that someone picks exactly the right variables during the modeling process in their first attempt?</p> <h2 id="the-value-of-modeling-chaos">The Value of Modeling Chaos</h2> <p>When models are capable of explaining observations, they can also be used as predictive tools depending on what kind of system is being represented. Of course, it does not make much sense to model a chaotic phenomenon and use the model in order to draw reliable predictions about the future. Thus, one should be mindful enough not to judge the value of a model solely based on its predictive power.</p> <p>But this does not mean that chaotic models simply cannot convey anything useful to us. While using chaotic models to predict an individual event might be useless, we can still picture their general behavior. It is similar to how scientists are not able to accurately predict the weather 30 days in advance, yet make claims about how the climate will behave in 30 years. In simple words, one must distinguish between an event and a statistics of a large number of events.</p> <p>The statistics of even chaotic or random events often exhibit characteristic patterns or features—uniform, normal, Poisson, binomial and geometric are some of the well-known distributions in this regard.</p> <p>For dynamical systems, a <strong>phase space</strong> is often constructed where each possible state of a system corresponds to a particular spatial location in a n-dimensional space. In the phase space could be various regions where most orbits get attracted towards—they could be fixed points, finite-period orbits or chaotic attractors in case of chaotic systems. One such chaotic attractor is the <strong>strange attractor</strong>, perhaps the most popular symbol or visual representation of chaos. Although we cannot exactly predict how an orbit will evolve over time for a chaotic system, we can still develop models that inform us about the attractors, repellers or other structures of potential interest.</p> <h2 id="context-is-everything-the-food-pyramid-example">Context is Everything: The Food Pyramid Example</h2> <p>A misconception that I would like to address is that more realistic models are necessarily better. I suppose we have all seen the pyramid diagram intended at guiding us to consuming a nutritious and balanced diet.</p> <p>This pyramid tells us a lot, but not everything. There are years of research and studies hidden behind this simple looking pyramid documented in the form of journals and research papers. Obviously, the abstract figure above misses a lot of information and we would surely learn a lot more by studying the research papers on food and nutrition. In a sense, those papers are more real and complete in comparison to this very basic diagram.</p> <p>However, which one do you find more effective in informing the general public about proper eating habits? What if now our target audience is a group of graduate students studying about human health and nutrition? Hopefully this clarifies why more abstract, less realistic models can often, but not always, be more useful or effective than the more realistic ones depending on what we intend to do with it.</p> <h2 id="models-as-knowledge-generators">Models as Knowledge Generators</h2> <p>Moreover, mathematical models are useful not only as tools to explain a phenomenon or predict its evolution, but also as <strong>tools for knowledge generation</strong>. In the pursuit of understanding a certain real-world phenomenon, asking the right questions plays an important role: a model can be of great help in this regard as well.</p> <p>Modeling is not a static process where we follow a sequence of steps and reach an end. Rather, we constantly question ourselves whether or not the model makes sense at each step. If it does not make sense at some point, we may have to revisit the earlier steps and make revisions to the model. When we gain new insights and knowledge from an existing model, several new hypotheses and questions usually arise out of that process.</p> <p>Even the discrepancies observed between the real-world phenomenon and the model can help generate more knowledge. As <strong>Kenneth E. Boulding</strong> said in <em>“Science: A Common Heritage”</em>, knowledge increases not only by the matching of images with the real world, that is, not by the direct perception of truth, but by the perception of error (Boulding). Thus, when we seek to explain the sources of discrepancies between the model and the real-world, even the unrealistic models—which most models are in fact—contribute to the advancement of knowledge.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>To summarize, a recurring idea throughout this essay has been about not losing sight of the context in which a model is employed. <strong>There can be no context-free, objective assessment of the usefulness of a model</strong>. Likewise, predictive power alone is not the all-important criterion for a model to be deemed useful—modeling is still highly important in order to learn about chaotic dynamical systems, even though they pose an inherent limitation to our predictability in practice.</p> <p>Furthermore, we should constantly remind ourselves that modeling might not be as enjoyable and fruitful if exploring the true essence of reality is our end goal—models are simply not constructed for that reason. <strong>The value of models lies in their ability to help us make sense of what we experience through our senses</strong>, or the senses of our instruments, with whatever resources we have: after all, we cannot escape the cave and explore the outside like Plato’s prisoners could.</p> <p>Mathematical models are widely used across numerous fields including engineering, economics, natural sciences, political science, sociology, and beyond. They seek to explain why a natural system works the way it does and also make predictions about its future in appropriate cases. Thus, models can be utilized to make data-driven strategies in various contexts such as choosing the most cost-effective waste-management strategy for a city, deciding the price of a product so as to maximize revenue, and countless other applications.</p> <p>The beauty of models lies not in their perfection, but in their imperfection—their deliberate simplification of reality that allows us to see patterns, relationships, and insights that would otherwise be lost in the overwhelming complexity of the real world. In being wrong about the details, they become right about what matters most.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h2> <p>Boulding, K.E. “Science: Our Common Heritage.” <em>Science</em> 207, no. 4433 (1980): 831-836.</p> <p>Box, George E.P. <em>Empirical Model-Building and Response Surfaces</em>. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1987.</p> <p>Choi, Charles Q. “Something from Nothing? A Vacuum Can Yield Flashes of Light.” <em>Scientific American</em>, 12 Feb. 2013. https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/something-from-nothing-vacuum-can-yield-flashes-of-light/.</p> <p>Frigg, Roman and Stephan Hartmann. “Models in Science.” <em>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</em> (Spring 2020 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.).</p> <p>Hesse, Mary. <em>Models and Analogies in Science</em>. London: Sheed and Ward, 1963.</p> <p>“The History of the Atom.” Socorro Independent School District. https://www.sisd.net/cms/lib/TX01001452/Centricity/Domain/1297/The_history_of_the_atom_Notes-_condensed.pdf.</p> <p>Whelan. “Plato’s Allegory of the Cave.” <em>Classical Wisdom Weekly</em>, 15 Jan. 2022. https://classicalwisdom.com/philosophy/platos-allegory-of-the-cave/.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematical-modeling"/><category term="modeling"/><category term="philosophy-of-science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We examine what makes a model truly useful—and how the best ones can be deliberately "wrong" to reveal deeper truths about the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Randomness vs Chaos: The Illusion of Pure Chance</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/randomness-vs-chaos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Randomness vs Chaos: The Illusion of Pure Chance"/><published>2022-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/randomness-vs-chaos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/randomness-vs-chaos/"><![CDATA[<p><em>“God does not play dice with the universe.”</em> This was Albert Einstein’s response (paraphrased) to the Nobel prize winning German physicist Max Born after Born suggested in a letter that the very fundamental nature of the quantum world was probabilistic. While the use of the word ‘God’ led many to believe that Einstein was a theist (which he denied later), I would like to draw your attention to something else in the statement—Einstein implied that a dice roll was random. What’s so interesting about that? That’s something we hear in our statistics class all the time, right?</p> <p>We will come back to this in a while, but for now, I want you to comment on two sequences of characters written below:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>aaaabbbbccccddddeeeeffffgggghhhhiiiijjjj
sdbcakjsquknwmsdkalajwnwouedskajakn
</code></pre></div></div> <p>How do you feel about these two strings? Do you think one is more ‘random’ than the other? To me, the first one feels much more ordered since it appears to have a pattern. However, the second one seems to arise from a cat sitting on my laptop keyboard and thus very ‘random’.</p> <p>If we think of a criterion that would help us formalize this understanding of ‘randomness’, perhaps we could comment on the degree of randomness of the strings based on our ability to express it more concisely, without losing any information. For instance, one way to compress the first string would be to write it as ‘a-j 4 × each’. However, it is extremely difficult to find a way to convey the second string clearly without spelling out each character; there simply isn’t any structure to exploit. In other words, it’s random. Well, this is what <strong>Gregory Chaitin</strong> refers to as true randomness. In Chaitin’s interpretation of randomness, the process by which a sequence is formed is not of much importance. All that’s important is the final sequence that we obtain and its structure (Chaitin).</p> <h2 id="the-illusion-of-randomness-in-our-world">The Illusion of Randomness in Our World</h2> <p>We use the word ‘random’ all the time, albeit mostly in a loose sense. In scientific terms, especially when discussing dynamical systems, the word <strong>‘random’</strong> has a precise meaning. To understand things that are random, let us first understand things that are not random.</p> <p>Firstly, a dice roll is not truly random: it follows the same set of rules that the rest of the objects in this world we experience follow. I’m sure Einstein implied that the dice roll was random as a metaphor, definitely not because he was unaware of this fact. When a leaf falls off a tree and dances its way in the air before landing on the ground, its trajectory feels so random, doesn’t it? As you might have guessed, even that movement is not random at all. Even most so-called ‘random number generators’ are not strictly random. In fact, I’d argue that there is hardly anything that we experience in the macroscopic world that is truly random in a strictly scientific sense.</p> <p>However, it’s not surprising at all that the events I’ve mentioned above are often perceived as being random. That’s completely reasonable because there are two ways to look at things: <strong>phenomenologically</strong> and <strong>ontologically</strong>. While phenomenology aims to describe the world around us based on how we experience it, ontology concerns itself not with an individual’s subjective experience but an objective description of the real world on a fundamental level.</p> <p>So what exactly is randomness and does randomness exist in the real world? Well, the word can have different meanings depending on the context, but for the sake of this essay, we define randomness in context of <strong>indeterminism</strong>.</p> <h2 id="defining-true-randomness">Defining True Randomness</h2> <p>An event is said to be <strong>random</strong> if it is not determined by anything, i.e. non-deterministic. The trajectory of a falling leaf is still determined by the flow of the air around it, the shape of the leaf and several other factors. I agree that we might not be able to track all these variables or fit them all coherently into a model. But that is not to say that the leaf follows a specific path without any cause.</p> <p><strong>Determinism</strong>, as we have discussed extensively previously, is when the present state of a system completely determines the future state. The entirety of classical physics is deterministic in nature (Feldman). This might suggest that we should be able to predict the future provided we devise a perfect model.</p> <p>Unfortunately, <strong>chaos</strong> prevents that from happening.</p> <h2 id="chaos-when-determinism-becomes-unpredictable">Chaos: When Determinism Becomes Unpredictable</h2> <p>A deterministic system is said to be <strong>chaotic</strong> if it is highly sensitive to small fluctuations in the initial conditions. <strong>SDIC (Sensitive Dependence on Initial Conditions)</strong> is a term widely used to characterize chaos, but that is only half the story.</p> <p>An exponential function without bounds can also have sensitive dependence on initial conditions, which can even be quantified via the <strong>Lyapunov exponent</strong>. Take any two different initial conditions \(x_0\) and \(y_0\). No matter how close these two are initially, when plugged into the iterated map \(x_{n+1} = 2x_n \Rightarrow x_n = 2^n x_0\), we get:</p> \[y_n - x_n = 2^n y_0 - 2^n x_0 = 2^n(y_0 - x_0)\] <p>This indicates that even the tiniest of differences in the initial condition is amplified at an exponential rate causing large differences in outcomes. But does this iterated map feel like chaos at all? The orbit traced by any initial condition is extremely confined in terms of how much it explores the available (phase) space. We expect things that are chaotic to really be all over the place, don’t we?</p> <p>That is why we impose another criterion for a system to be called chaotic. A chaotic system demonstrates some kind of <strong>‘stretching and folding’</strong> mechanism which leads to not only nearby points being stretched far away but also distant points coming arbitrarily close as a result of the folding (Bishop).</p> <p>The simplest way to see this in action is to observe the process of kneading a dough. Kneading a dough is basically performing the stretching and folding action again and again—two very nearby particles on the dough get stretched away far from each other while some particles initially far away from each other come close to each other during the folding process. This is what causes chaotic dynamical systems to remain bounded and not drift away to infinity like in the doubling map we saw earlier.</p> <h2 id="the-quantum-realm-where-true-randomness-may-exist">The Quantum Realm: Where True Randomness May Exist</h2> <p>Coming back to the discussion of randomness, if most of what we perceive as random is in fact deterministic chaos in disguise, is there anything random in this world at all? It turns out that the real world could be random on the quantum scale. But how exactly can we know what reality is? I do not have a definitive answer to this, but let’s leave that discussion for later.</p> <p>Perhaps one of the most widely heard principles surrounding quantum mechanics is the <strong>Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle</strong>, formulated by Nobel Laureate and German physicist Werner Heisenberg. No, it does not say that 2 times 3 may not be equal to 3 times 2 because of the uncertainty. This argument was made by Dr. B.M Hegde, an Indian professor and a strong proponent of quantum healing, no surprise there (“Is E = mc2 wrong? – Dr. B M Hegde”, 0:40 - 1:05).</p> <p>Rather, the <strong>Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle</strong> states that there is a fundamental limit to the accuracy with which we can measure both the position and momentum of a particle; the more we know about one, the lesser we know about the other. More precisely, if \(\Delta x\) and \(\Delta p\) are the uncertainties associated with the position and momentum of a particle, then \(\Delta x \Delta p \geq \frac{h}{4\pi}\), where \(h\) is the Planck’s constant which is about \(6.626 \times 10^{-34} \text{ J·s}\).</p> <p>The principle makes it clear that the inaccuracy in measurement does not arise from human error but from an inherent restriction posed by nature. As a result, we can no longer associate one particular present state of a system with its future state like we could for deterministic events (“Heisenberg’s Uncertainty Principle”).</p> <h2 id="the-hidden-variable-debate">The Hidden Variable Debate</h2> <p>Now, one thought that could strike our mind is what if the uncertainty is not really fundamental and maybe there is something behind the bushes that we just haven’t discovered yet. Apparently, Einstein and several other physicists of the time, including Louis de Broglie and David Bohm, thought along the same lines.</p> <p>Einstein, not convinced about the non-deterministic nature of quantum phenomena, made an unsuccessful attempt to formulate a <strong>hidden-variable theory</strong> hoping to explain quantum phenomena as deterministic events instead. De Broglie also came up with a deterministic hidden-variable theory whereby a ‘pilot wave’ guides the trajectory of a particle—this theory didn’t gain much success and ended up being abandoned by de Broglie himself (Baggott).</p> <p>Numerous experiments and observations overwhelmingly support the assertion that quantum theory is fundamentally probabilistic in nature. Thus, quantum events could possibly be the only events that are truly random in nature.</p> <h2 id="bridging-the-quantum-classical-divide">Bridging the Quantum-Classical Divide</h2> <p>The above statement should raise a striking question. Since everything in the macroscopic world is made up of atoms that function in quantum scales, how can the macroscopic world be deterministic if the quantum world is non-deterministic?</p> <p>To understand this, we should differentiate between an individual, possibly random, event and the statistics of a large number of such events. For example, assuming that an unbiased coin toss is random, it is difficult to accurately predict which side the coin flips next. However, when we flip the coin a million times, we can expect the number of heads and tails to be approximately 500,000 each with some margin of error.</p> <p>In a similar way, even though we cannot predict the behavior of a single quantum particle, we can still know the average behavior of a large number of quantum particles. In a way, their behavior ‘averages out’ by the <strong>law of large numbers</strong> (Dekking). We simply need not worry about how one quantum particle happens to behave when working at a macroscopic scale.</p> <h2 id="distinguishing-chaos-from-randomness">Distinguishing Chaos from Randomness</h2> <p>To summarize the difference between chaos and randomness, <strong>chaos</strong> is a property of some dynamical systems that rules out any possibility of accurate prediction arbitrarily far into the future even though the system itself is completely determined by its present state. On the other hand, <strong>true randomness</strong> only exists for a system such that its present or past does not determine its future, not even in theory.</p> <p>However, for all practical purposes, we often use the word randomness to describe chaotic events whose outcome we can neither determine beforehand nor influence by any means.</p> <p>In fact, it is not possible to say for sure whether an event is random or chaotic just through the set of observations or their statistics. A fair coin toss can be reasonably called random unless people learn how to rig a coin toss. After all, researchers at the University of British Columbia found out that some simple instructions on manipulating a coin toss and a few minutes of practice was sufficient for more than half of the participants in a study to significantly manipulate the outcome of a coin toss (Clark).</p> <h2 id="the-nature-of-reality-models-vs-truth">The Nature of Reality: Models vs Truth</h2> <p>Having said all these, an important question still remains, and might remain for a long, long time. What is it that we are characterizing as chaotic or random? Are we really describing the true nature of reality or just the models we build in hope of understanding the real world?</p> <p>In fact, I would argue that whatever we experience as reality is not true reality. Instead, it is our brain that develops models of reality based on data fed by our senses, an idea that Stephen Hawking agrees with. My point here is that our understanding of reality is driven by models; in some sense, we could be experiencing the reality of a really good model, still not perfect—optical illusions like the flash lag illusion exemplify this.</p> <p>The better the model is at explaining observations, the closer we find it to reality. Therefore, we can always strive for better models that explain our experiences better but still unable to really explain the true nature of reality. In this sense, I am hesitant to call the differences between randomness and chaos as objective.</p> <p>In fact, I suggest that we reflect on <strong>Niels Bohr’s</strong> idea that the task of physics is not to find out how nature is—physics concerns what we say about nature instead (Petersen). So, while the ideas of determinism and non-determinism, chaos and randomness help us describe our experiences and observations, those might not characterize true reality.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>What true reality is, we may never know. But in our quest to understand the world around us, the distinction between randomness and chaos provides a powerful framework for thinking about predictability, determinism, and the fundamental nature of events.</p> <p>While chaos emerges from deterministic systems that are simply too sensitive to initial conditions for practical prediction, true randomness—if it exists—represents a more fundamental break from causality. Whether we’re dealing with the chaotic dance of a falling leaf or the quantum uncertainty of subatomic particles, recognizing these distinctions helps us better understand both the power and limitations of our predictive capabilities.</p> <p>Perhaps Einstein was right that God doesn’t play dice with the universe. But even if the universe is fundamentally deterministic, chaos ensures that it often <em>appears</em> as if someone is rolling the dice—and that appearance may be all that matters for our lived experience of reality.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h2> <p>Baggott, Jim. <em>The Quantum Story: A History in 40 Moments</em>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2011. Pp. 116-117.</p> <p>Bishop, Robert. “Chaos.” <em>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</em> (Spring 2017 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.).</p> <p>Chaitin, Gregory. “The Chaitin Interview II: Defining Randomness.” Interview by Robert J. Marks. March 2021.</p> <p>Clark, M. P. A., and B. D. Westerberg. “How Random Is the Toss of a Coin?” <em>Canadian Medical Association Journal</em>, vol. 181, no. 12, CMA Joule Inc., Dec. 2009, pp. E306–08. https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.091733.</p> <p>Dekking, Michel. <em>A Modern Introduction to Probability and Statistics</em>. Springer, 2005. pp. 181-190.</p> <p>“E=mc² is wrong? - Dr. B M Hegde.” YouTube, uploaded by Dr. B M Hegde Fans Club, 27 September 2021. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0DxrSGAwSGk.</p> <p>Feldman, David P. “Newton, Laplace, and Determinism.” <em>Chaos and Fractals: An Elementary Introduction</em>. Oxford: Oxford Academic, 2012.</p> <p>“Heisenberg’s Uncertainty Principle.” <em>Chemistry LibreTexts</em>, 11 Sept. 2022. https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Physical_and_Theoretical_Chemistry_Textbook_Maps/Supplemental_Modules_(Physical_and_Theoretical_Chemistry)/Quantum_Mechanics/02._Fundamental_Concepts_of_Quantum_Mechanics/Heisenberg’s_Uncertainty_Principle.</p> <p>Murphy, Paul Austin. “Stephen Hawking’s Philosophy: Model-Dependent Realism.” <em>Medium</em>, 15 Dec. 2021. https://medium.com/science-and-philosophy/stephen-hawkings-model-dependent-realism-2b2973af41a6.</p> <p>Petersen, Aage. “The Philosophy of Niels Bohr.” <em>Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists</em>, vol. 19, no. 7, 1963, pp. 8–14. https://doi.org/10.1080/00963402.1963.11454520.</p> <p><em>The Born–Einstein letters: correspondence between Albert Einstein and Max and Hedwig Born from 1916–1955, with commentaries by Max Born</em>. London: Macmillan, 1971. p. 91.</p> <p>“What Is the Uncertainty Principle and Why Is It Important?” <em>Caltech Science Exchange</em>. https://scienceexchange.caltech.edu/topics/quantum-science-explained/uncertainty-principle.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematical-modeling"/><category term="randomness"/><category term="chaos"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We look at the line between randomness and chaos, uncovering how many seemingly random events are actually driven by hidden deterministic rules—and asking whether this distinction speaks to the nature of reality or just to the limits of how we model it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Models: The Art of Mathematical Simplification</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/making-models-the-art-of-mathematical-simplification/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Models: The Art of Mathematical Simplification"/><published>2022-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/making-models-the-art-of-mathematical-simplification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/making-models-the-art-of-mathematical-simplification/"><![CDATA[<p><em>“For the first time in over 150 years, there is solid evidence that the solar system’s planetary census is incomplete.”</em> These are the words from Konstantin Batygin, a Caltech researcher and professor of planetary science, who claimed to have found a ninth planet in our solar system, “Planet Nine” (Drake). The intriguing part, however, is that the so-called Planet Nine has not been observed by astronomers yet.</p> <p>How legitimate should such a claim be considered then? Coming from researchers from one of the leading research universities in the world, I do not think the claim is completely baseless and unfounded. Turns out, it was not just a random guess but a conclusion derived from evidence gained from a <strong>mathematical model</strong>.</p> <h2 id="what-makes-a-model-mathematical">What Makes a Model Mathematical?</h2> <p>What is a mathematical model in the first place and how is it useful to us? A <strong>mathematical model</strong> is a systematic framework that uses mathematical language to represent and analyze real-world phenomena—including phenomena that may be impossible for humans to observe directly. Rather than being merely a collection of equations, models serve as bridges between abstract mathematical concepts and tangible reality.</p> <p>Since mathematics provides a language of rigor and precision, mathematical equations are preferably used to represent real-world phenomena in models. However, all models are not necessarily mathematical; models can also be physical or conceptual. Once a model of a natural phenomenon is devised, it can be used to gain a deeper understanding of the phenomenon, revealing insights which would otherwise be difficult, or even impossible, to observe in the real world.</p> <p>For example, provided we know sufficiently the laws of physics at the atomic scale, we can model the structures of atoms, molecules and compounds by making some assumptions that help us simplify the real-world complex nature of atoms. In this case, it is not hard to see that the model will not give the exact picture of an atom because some information is inevitably lost after making the simplifying assumptions.</p> <h2 id="the-power-and-necessity-of-assumptions">The Power and Necessity of Assumptions</h2> <p><strong>Assumptions</strong> are indeed an integral part of any model as long as they can be justified. It is important to realize that a model is only as good as its assumptions and that assumptions often limit the scope of the model.</p> <p>Models used to study populations of animal species usually consider the population to grow at a rate proportional to its current size, provided there are no factors that limit the growth—this results in an exponential growth. While some populations might exhibit exponential growth for a short period of time, the population cannot grow that rapidly at all times. Eventually and inevitably, factors such as insufficient food and resources will limit the population growth.</p> <p>Thus, the model would fail at representing the population growth because of faults in the underlying assumption over a long time period. However, when the species population is small and resources are abundant, the model can be of good use. Here, the underlying assumption greatly reduced the mathematical complexity of the model, while also limiting the scope of its usability.</p> <p>Even the great Sir Isaac Newton assumed the Earth—and masses in general—to be a <strong>point mass</strong>, i.e. all the mass is confined to a single point at its center when devising his models for gravitation (Yang). As ridiculous as it may seem to assume that a mass of 6 billion trillion metric tons acts at a single point, it does have a valid justification and did the trick for Newton.</p> <p>Due to this and several other assumptions that Newton made in devising a model for gravitation, his model cannot correctly explain every gravitational phenomenon. Beyond exotic cases like black holes, even more commonplace phenomena such as ocean tides and the precession of Earth’s axis require more sophisticated treatment than point-mass approximations can provide. Thus, the scope of his model was diminished, but the model proved extremely useful in the field of cosmology.</p> <p>It is now clear that upon making the simplifying assumptions, models deviate even further from reality. This begs an important question: should a good model prioritize realism or simplicity?</p> <h2 id="simplicity-over-realism-the-counter-intuitive-truth">Simplicity Over Realism: The Counter-Intuitive Truth</h2> <p>Truth be told, it is not the aim of a mathematical model, in general, to replicate exactly a real-world situation by fitting in as much detail as possible. In a sense, it is rather the opposite—<strong>a good model should be as simple and general as possible</strong>. What are models supposed to do then? They should provide insight, enable prediction within defined bounds, and reveal the essential mechanisms driving a phenomenon. Complicating the model by crowding every little feature about the phenomenon we know of might make the model more realistic, but not necessarily better at achieving these core objectives.</p> <p>Well, there are certain models that try to make use of every information at their disposal to give a more realistic picture of the real-world phenomenon—we call them <strong>simulations</strong>. However, the utility of simulations differs greatly from that of other models. Simulations are mostly used in cases where we wish to understand the workings of a very particular system. As a result, simulations do not offer much help when it comes to generalizing the result in a broader context.</p> <p>For example: in order to decide a suitable design for a skyscraper that needs to meet specifications as requested on some island in Abu Dhabi that experiences high heat and wind speeds, simulations are the perfect tool. However, we may not be able to generalize the simulation results from this very particular situation easily to the construction of buildings in general. On the other hand, there can be some fundamental and general ideas relevant to all sorts of construction which can be expressed in the form of models.</p> <h2 id="all-models-are-wrong-but-some-are-useful">All Models Are Wrong, But Some Are Useful</h2> <p>Statistician George Box famously wrote that <em>“all models are wrong, but some are useful”</em> (Box, “Empirical Model-Building and Response Surfaces”). The first part of the quote is no surprise. If we expect a model to be a true representation of the real world, then there is no doubt that most models are wrong in that aspect. But does that make models useless? Well, I’m tempted to believe in George Box when he claims even wrong models can be useful.</p> <p>After all, how accurate is a flat two-dimensional map of the three-dimensional world? Far from accurate (Mason). How useful is it though? Pretty useful I reckon. A map, although not mathematical, is still a modeling of the real world. However, a natural question arises here: why is every piece of information regarding the system not incorporated in a model?</p> <p>We have partly answered this in our above discussion of making simplifying assumptions. It is true that formulating clear assumptions makes the equations less messy and more manageable. However, there is something more to it, which becomes clearer when we begin to understand the objectives of devising a model of a natural phenomenon.</p> <h2 id="understanding-through-mathematical-relationships">Understanding Through Mathematical Relationships</h2> <p>Firstly, by expressing the workings of a system in a mathematical way through models, the relationship among variables and their particular roles in the system can be understood better. This, in return, provides greater insights about the system that is being modeled. To accomplish this, we only consider the relevant variables in the system.</p> <p>For instance, to model the motion of a falling object, if we are interested in investigating the relationship between the distance fallen and the time elapsed, we may assume the resistive forces like air friction to be negligible.</p> <p>The Greek philosopher Aristotle believed that when two objects—one heavier than the other—are dropped from a height, the heavier object falls faster. This belief was held for almost 2000 years until Galileo Galilei discovered that provided no air friction, two objects dropped simultaneously from a height, no matter their masses, reach the ground at the same time. Galileo concluded that the distance fallen was proportional to the square of the time elapsed for any object dropped from a height in the absence of air friction (Lienhard).</p> <p>Notice that even Galileo’s conclusion about the falling bodies does not hold for a coin and feather dropped under normal conditions. However, Galileo clearly prescribed the conditions necessary for his model to provide accurate results in the form of assumptions, something which Aristotle didn’t. This illustrates the crucial importance of clearly stating a model’s scope and limitations.</p> <h2 id="modeling-the-unpredictable-chaos-and-its-insights">Modeling the Unpredictable: Chaos and Its Insights</h2> <p>So far, we have looked at models for stable systems that allow for making reasonable future predictions. But a large number of real-world systems are <strong>chaotic</strong> in nature, thus posing significant challenges in making future predictions. Why model something that we cannot predict?</p> <p>Well, even to discover the chaotic nature of systems, it can sometimes be necessary to model it properly first. The factor causing chaos in systems can be found embedded within the mathematical equations most of the time. While a system can have several parameters, only a few might contribute to its instability. Thus, correctly identifying such parameters with the aid of models will tell us which parameters to focus on in order to increase our predictive power despite all limitations.</p> <p>After all, fine-tuning a parameter whose uncertainty does not even grow with time with sophisticated technology and equipment will not give high returns and can be a waste of time and resources. In recent years, scientists have begun employing machine learning algorithms successfully to stretch the time period for which the prediction of a chaotic system can be made (Wolchover). Therefore, while acknowledging the impossibility of predictions arbitrarily far into the future for chaotic systems, we must not forget that shorter term prediction is still possible and is a growing field in the STEM world.</p> <h2 id="models-as-knowledge-generators">Models as Knowledge Generators</h2> <p>Moreover, mathematical models are useful not only as tools to explain a phenomenon or predict its evolution within certain timeframes, but also as <strong>tools for knowledge generation</strong>. In the pursuit of understanding a certain real-world phenomenon, asking the right questions plays an important role: a model can be of great help in this regard as well.</p> <p>Modeling is not a static process where we follow a sequence of steps and reach an end. Rather, we constantly question ourselves whether or not the model makes sense at each step. If it does not make sense at some point, we may have to revisit the earlier steps and make revisions to the model. When we gain new insights and knowledge from an existing model, several new hypotheses and questions usually arise out of that process.</p> <p>Even the discrepancies observed between the real-world phenomenon and the model can help generate more knowledge. As Kenneth E. Boulding said in <em>“Science: A Common Heritage”</em>, knowledge increases not only by the matching of images with the real world, that is, not by the direct perception of truth, but by the perception of error (Boulding). Thus, when we seek to explain the sources of discrepancies between the model and the real-world, even the unrealistic models—which most models are in fact—contribute to the advancement of knowledge.</p> <h2 id="the-broader-impact-of-mathematical-modeling">The Broader Impact of Mathematical Modeling</h2> <p>Mathematical models are widely used across numerous fields including engineering, economics, natural sciences, political science, and sociology. They seek to explain why a natural system works the way it does and also make predictions about its future in appropriate cases. Thus, models can be utilized in order to make data-driven strategies in various contexts such as choosing the most cost-effective waste-management strategy for a city, deciding the price of a product so as to maximize revenue, and countless other applications.</p> <p>Moreover, models are also important tools for advancing our existing knowledge of real-world phenomena since they can propel us to ask the right questions, create and test new hypotheses, as well as investigate the cause of any discrepancy that is observed with respect to the real world.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>As useful as models are, it turns out that they are least useful in doing what might be generally expected of them—representing the real-world phenomenon with perfect accuracy. At best, a model is a good approximation to the underlying truth of natural phenomena and should not be mistaken for being the truth itself.</p> <p>Mathematical models are mathematical representations of real-world phenomena built from our existing scientific knowledge and experimentation. Their true power lies not in their realism, but in their ability to reveal essential relationships, generate insights, and guide our understanding of complex systems. When we embrace their limitations while leveraging their strengths, models become indispensable tools for both understanding our world and shaping our future within it.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h2> <p>Boulding, K.E. “Science: Our Common Heritage.” Science 207, no. 4433 (1980): 831-836.</p> <p>Box, George E.P. “Science and Statistics.” Journal of the American Statistical Association 71, no. 356 (1976): 791-799.</p> <p>Box, George E.P., and Norman R. Draper. <em>Empirical Model-Building and Response Surfaces</em>. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1987.</p> <p>Drake, Nadia. “Planet 9 may be closer and easier to find than thought—if it exists.” <em>National Geographic</em>, August 2021. https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/planet-9-may-be-closer-and-easier-to-find-than-thought-if-it-exists.</p> <p>Lienhard, John H. “Galileo’s Experiment.” <em>Engines of Our Ingenuity</em>. University of Houston. https://www.uh.edu/engines/epi166.htm.</p> <p>Mason, Betsy. “Why your mental map of the world is (probably) wrong.” <em>National Geographic</em>, November 2018. https://www.nationalgeographic.com/culture/article/all-over-the-map-mental-mapping-misconceptions.</p> <p>Wolchover, Natalie. “Machine Learning’s ‘Amazing’ Ability to Predict Chaos.” <em>Quanta Magazine</em>, April 18, 2018. https://www.quantamagazine.org/machine-learnings-amazing-ability-to-predict-chaos-20180418/.</p> <p>Yang, Xin-She. <em>Engineering Mathematics with Examples and Applications</em>. Cambridge, MA: Academic Press, 2017.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematical-modeling"/><category term="modeling"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This piece explores what it means to model a natural phenomenon mathematically, the variety of models we use, and what they can still teach us—even when small uncertainties make long-term behavior unpredictable.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Determinism and Unpredictability</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/determinism-and-unpredictability/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Determinism and Unpredictability"/><published>2022-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/determinism-and-unpredictability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/al-folio/blog/2022/determinism-and-unpredictability/"><![CDATA[<p><em>September 15, 2022</em></p> <h2 id="the-predictable-and-the-unpredictable">The Predictable and the Unpredictable</h2> <p>If I throw a ball—heavy enough not to be swayed by wind or other natural forces except gravity, or in a vacuum—the laws of physics give us a way to make reasonable approximations of how high the ball reaches, how far it travels, and how long it remains in the air. This is, of course, valid only when I am well-informed about the ball’s initial velocity and launch angle. The accuracy of my approximation depends mostly on the accuracy of my knowledge of the ball’s initial state.</p> <p>Had science not given us a way to foresee future consequences based on our present state and actions, would astronauts ever be able to travel back and forth to the ISS at the rate they do now? Certainly not. In fact, there are countless everyday scenarios where we make use of our ability to predict future outcomes based on our knowledge of how things work, albeit mostly tentatively without heavy mathematical computations.</p> <p>While most of us might not have given it much thought, we have internalized that outcomes to most of our actions are not random—that the consequences we face are mostly due to specific causes we may or may not be aware of. I use the word “most” rather than “each and every” because for some actions, some of us might feel the results are somewhat random. For instance, when we toss a coin, we cannot say with certainty which side it will land on. Some might describe the outcome as “random” and equally likely to be heads or tails.</p> <h2 id="laplaces-vision-of-determinism">Laplace’s Vision of Determinism</h2> <p>But is this truly the case? Is a coin toss inherently random? What causes this apparent randomness? <strong>Pierre-Simon Laplace</strong>, a scholar and polymath, believed that nothing in the universe is truly random. Based on Laplace’s belief, our failure to predict coin tosses with certainty could be attributed to two potential reasons:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Imperfect Models</strong>: We might not have a perfect model for a coin toss that ties all dependent variables—such as the coin’s orientation, initial velocity, surrounding air currents, etc.—in a complete and correct way.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Uncertain Parameters</strong>: Even if we devised a perfect model for coin tosses, our knowledge of the parameters will inevitably have some uncertainty. For some systems (including coin tosses), even minuscule uncertainties can snowball into large errors in the final result.</p> </li> </ol> <p>In principle, if we could overcome these two limitations, there would be no suspense to a coin flip—we would get it right every time. Thus, the randomness we perceive would just be the byproduct of our imperfect knowledge about the initial state and laws of the system.</p> <p>Speaking more generally, Laplace believed that if we knew precisely the present state of a <strong>dynamical system</strong>—a system whose state variables change over time according to specific rules—and the rules that act upon that state, we could determine how the present state evolves into a future state, possibly one arbitrarily far in the future. This is what we refer to as a <strong>deterministic system</strong>.</p> <p>We can refer to the laws governing a deterministic dynamical system as <em>“the rule of evolution”</em> as it controls how an anterior state evolves into a later one. In a deterministic system, an action can have one, and only one, consequence—had there been multiple possible consequences, the system would be random, not deterministic. Thus, <strong>randomness</strong> (also called stochasticism) and <strong>determinism</strong> can be thought of as opposites of each other.</p> <h3 id="the-quantum-caveat">The Quantum Caveat</h3> <p>To clarify, the examples I gave above about throwing the ball and the coin toss are believed to follow the laws of Newtonian physics, which are completely deterministic in nature. However, when we look at the quantum side of physics, there seem to exist intrinsically random aspects. So, the universe may not be fully deterministic as Laplace believed. The scientific community is still divided on this issue, and I do not wish to give any verdict here. However, the models we use to describe the real world can be deterministic or non-deterministic.</p> <h2 id="when-determinism-doesnt-guarantee-predictability">When Determinism Doesn’t Guarantee Predictability</h2> <p>Stochastic systems, by their very nature, limit our ability to predict the future. However, as counterintuitive as it may sound, <strong>predictability is not always guaranteed even for deterministic systems</strong>. Systems could be completely deterministic and yet it might be impossible for us to reasonably predict future states.</p> <p>The exception would be if the hypothetical intelligence Laplace discussed in his <em>“A Philosophical Essay on Probabilities”</em> existed in reality, which it does not and never will. Laplace wrote:</p> <blockquote> <p><em>Given for one instant an intelligence which could comprehend all the forces by which nature is animated and the respective situation of the beings who compose it—an intelligence sufficiently vast to submit these data to analysis—it would embrace in the same formula the movements of the greatest bodies of the universe and those of the lightest atom; for it, nothing would be uncertain and the future, as the past, would be present to its eyes.</em></p> </blockquote> <p>It is now imperative for us to discuss why such unpredictability exists even for some completely deterministic systems. While flaws in the evolution rule itself could be one reason, the unpredictability could persist even when we have a perfect evolution rule.</p> <h3 id="comparing-astronomy-and-meteorology">Comparing Astronomy and Meteorology</h3> <p>Within deterministic systems, there are systems for which accurate predictions can be made. For instance, astronomers can predict the position of stars and the timings of eclipses even 10 years from now based on deterministic models and observational data. However, it would be extremely difficult for meteorologists to accurately predict the weather of a location one month later.</p> <p>Is this simply because astronomers are more skilled and advanced than meteorologists? Not at all.</p> <h2 id="the-mathematics-of-uncertainty">The Mathematics of Uncertainty</h2> <p>Firstly, we need to understand that <strong>no measurement done on a continuous scale is completely free of errors</strong>—the limitations of the measuring instrument and the skill of the experimenter both play a role. As former MIT Professor Walter Lewin said in his lectures, any measurement we make without knowledge of its uncertainty is completely meaningless.</p> <p>This is why all credible scientific papers containing observational data also include the uncertainties associated with them. The uncertainties—depending on the kind of model we’re using—can remain constant, grow (linearly or nonlinearly), or even shrink with time.</p> <h3 id="case-1-constant-uncertainty">Case 1: Constant Uncertainty</h3> <p>Let’s start with an example where uncertainty remains constant. Suppose we track the velocity of a ball dropped from a height with some initial velocity at each second of its fall. For simplicity, let’s assume air resistance is negligible and gravitational acceleration is constant. We can model this scenario with:</p> \[v_{t+1} = v_t + g \cdot \Delta t\] <p>where \(v_t\) is the velocity of the ball in m/s at time \(t\), \(g\) is gravitational acceleration in m/s², and \(\Delta t\) is the time interval (1 second in our case).</p> <p>Starting with an initial velocity of 0 m/s:</p> \[\begin{align*} v_0 &amp;= 0 \\ v_1 &amp;= v_0 + g \cdot \Delta t = g \cdot \Delta t \\ v_2 &amp;= v_1 + g \cdot \Delta t = 2g \cdot \Delta t \\ &amp;\vdots \\ v_n &amp;= v_{n-1} + g \cdot \Delta t = ng \cdot \Delta t \end{align*}\] <p>Now, let’s see the results when we have an uncertainty of \(\Delta v_0\) in the initial velocity:</p> \[\begin{align*} v_0 &amp;= 0 + \Delta v_0 = \Delta v_0 \\ v_1 &amp;= v_0 + g \cdot \Delta t = \Delta v_0 + g \cdot \Delta t \\ v_2 &amp;= v_1 + g \cdot \Delta t = \Delta v_0 + 2g \cdot \Delta t \\ &amp;\vdots \\ v_n &amp;= v_{n-1} + g \cdot \Delta t = \Delta v_0 + ng \cdot \Delta t \end{align*}\] <p>As we can see clearly, the initial uncertainty neither grows nor shrinks. It remains constant, and therefore, if we ensure that the uncertainty is small to start with, it will have an insignificant bearing on the final results. In this scenario, <strong>the system is both deterministic and predictable</strong>.</p> <h3 id="case-2-growing-and-shrinking-uncertainty">Case 2: Growing and Shrinking Uncertainty</h3> <p>However, there are equations for which the initial uncertainty changes over time. Let’s examine this mathematical equation:</p> \[x_{n+1} = k \cdot x_n\] <p>Although it’s unlikely that real-world phenomena can be exactly translated into this equation, it is embedded within several actual equations used to model real-world phenomena. Thus, we can gain valuable insights from this simple recurrence relation.</p> <p>Listing out the first few terms:</p> \[\begin{align*} x_1 &amp;= k \cdot x_0 \\ x_2 &amp;= k \cdot x_1 = k^2 \cdot x_0 \\ x_3 &amp;= k \cdot x_2 = k^3 \cdot x_0 \\ &amp;\vdots \\ x_n &amp;= k^n \cdot x_0 \end{align*}\] <p>Now, let’s add an uncertainty of \(\Delta x_0\) to \(x_0\) and observe what changes:</p> \[\begin{align*} x_1 &amp;= k(x_0 + \Delta x_0) = k \cdot x_0 + k \cdot \Delta x_0 \\ x_2 &amp;= k \cdot x_1 = k^2 \cdot x_0 + k^2 \cdot \Delta x_0 \\ x_3 &amp;= k \cdot x_2 = k^3 \cdot x_0 + k^3 \cdot \Delta x_0 \\ &amp;\vdots \\ x_n &amp;= k^n \cdot x_0 + k^n \cdot \Delta x_0 \end{align*}\] <p>Here, an initial uncertainty of \(\Delta x_0\) has translated into \(k^n \cdot \Delta x_0\) after \(n\) iterations. What happens to the uncertainty is determined by the value of \(k\):</p> <ul> <li>If <strong>\(k &gt; 1\)</strong>: uncertainty grows exponentially</li> <li>If <strong>\(k &lt; -1\)</strong>: uncertainty still grows exponentially, but \(x_n\) also displays oscillatory behavior</li> <li>If <strong>\(-1 &lt; k &lt; 1\)</strong>: uncertainty shrinks with each iteration</li> </ul> <p>Let’s see this in action with a numerical example:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>n</th> <th>\(k = 3\)</th> <th>\(k = 3\) (with uncertainty)</th> <th>\(k = -5\)</th> <th>\(k = -5\) (with uncertainty)</th> <th>\(k = 0.5\)</th> <th>\(k = 0.5\) (with uncertainty)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>0</td> <td>2</td> <td>2.2</td> <td>2</td> <td>2.2</td> <td>2000</td> <td>2200</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>6</td> <td>6.6</td> <td>-10</td> <td>-11</td> <td>1000</td> <td>1100</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>18</td> <td>19.8</td> <td>50</td> <td>55</td> <td>500</td> <td>550</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td>54</td> <td>59.4</td> <td>-250</td> <td>-275</td> <td>250</td> <td>275</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>162</td> <td>178.2</td> <td>1250</td> <td>1375</td> <td>125</td> <td>137.5</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>486</td> <td>534.6</td> <td>-6250</td> <td>-6875</td> <td>62.5</td> <td>68.75</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10</td> <td>118,098</td> <td>129,907.8</td> <td>19,531,250</td> <td>21,484,375</td> <td>1.95</td> <td>2.15</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <h2 id="stable-vs-unstable-equilibrium">Stable vs. Unstable Equilibrium</h2> <p>This simple equation and similar ones manifest themselves in certain dynamical systems. When <strong>\(k &gt; 1\)</strong> or <strong>\(k &lt; -1\)</strong>, it gives rise to <em>“unstable equilibrium”</em>; when <strong>\(-1 &lt; k &lt; 1\)</strong>, it causes <em>“stable equilibrium”</em>.</p> <p>Roughly speaking, an object is in <strong>equilibrium</strong> if it is in a balanced state. A simple pendulum at rest hanging down, or precisely upwards, is in equilibrium; a spring when it is neither compressed nor stretched is in equilibrium.</p> <h3 id="an-analogy-for-understanding-stability">An Analogy for Understanding Stability</h3> <p>Let’s understand stable and unstable equilibrium with a simple analogy. When I stand straight upright, I am in a state of balance, or equilibrium. If someone pushes me slightly when I am upright, it will not affect my equilibrium much—I have the tendency to return to my equilibrium state even when some force is applied to unbalance me. This is called <strong>stable equilibrium</strong>.</p> <p>A better example of <strong>unstable equilibrium</strong> is a pen balanced on its pointed tip. Theoretically, there exists an equilibrium position where the pen could remain perfectly upright. However, in practice, you will never observe a pen remaining at rest in this position—even the tiniest disturbance (which always exists due to air currents, vibrations, or measurement uncertainties) will cause it to fall over immediately. Unlike the stable equilibrium, where small perturbations are resisted, unstable equilibrium amplifies even infinitesimal disturbances.</p> <h3 id="the-double-pendulum-example">The Double Pendulum Example</h3> <p>In dynamical systems that exhibit unstable equilibrium, a tiny nudge can be enough to completely halt the state of equilibrium. If we knew precisely the “tiny nudge,” there would still be ways to predict the future. However, most of the time, the nudge is so small that it falls within the range of our uncertainty.</p> <p>For instance, if I could measure a certain force to be 20N with an uncertainty of 0.5N, I would be unable to differentiate any two forces in the range of 19.5N to 20.5N. However, that margin of error could be sufficient to cause large disruptions in unstable systems, and we would never be able to predict the future for such systems well enough.</p> <p>A real-life example of such phenomenon is a <strong>classic double pendulum</strong>. No matter how hard we try, we will not be able to release two double pendulums in any way such that both trace the same path at all times, even though we know very well the equations that govern the motion of the double pendulum. This is because even if we feel like we have released the two pendulums from the same position, there will surely be a difference in the two positions—small enough for us not to notice—that will eventually snowball into a large difference.</p> <p>It again boils down to our ignorance of the system’s state, even when we are equipped with precise evolution rules. Therefore, <strong>predictability is unfeasible for unstable systems even when the system is completely deterministic</strong> because of our lack of precise knowledge of its initial state.</p> <h2 id="the-birth-of-chaos-theory">The Birth of Chaos Theory</h2> <p>Let’s shift our focus to weather forecasting and meteorology. <strong>Edward Lorenz</strong>, an outstanding meteorologist from the 20th century, tried to fit mathematics into meteorology through the use of first-generation computers, a recent invention during his time. Lorenz used deterministic differential equations to model the atmosphere by taking into account the most important factors such as temperature, air pressure, and humidity.</p> <p>It was going well for him until he encountered what he thought was a computer malfunction, which he later figured out was not a malfunction at all. Instead, Lorenz had plugged in the rounded version of a number (0.506 instead of 0.506127) when he tried to repeat his simulation at a later time. After all, a difference of a thousandth would surely be inconsequential in the calculations, wouldn’t it?</p> <p>To his surprise, the same model and equations displayed completely different results. While others in the past ruled out such erratic behavior as caused by some other faults, <strong>Lorenz realized that the random-looking outcomes were born out of the deterministic equations themselves</strong>.</p> <h3 id="the-butterfly-effect">The Butterfly Effect</h3> <p>Lorenz then used the word <strong>“chaos”</strong> to refer to such behavior—<em>sensitive dependence on initial conditions</em>. Chaos is sometimes used interchangeably with <em>“the butterfly effect”</em> to describe phenomena where slight differences in the initial conditions can lead to large differences in the outcome.</p> <p>Because the atmosphere is generally unstable, Lorenz ruled out the possibility of being able to successfully predict weather patterns over a long duration—weeks or months from now. <strong>Chaos eliminates the possibility of predicting the state of unstable/chaotic systems arbitrarily far into the future</strong>: no matter how small the error is to start with, it will eventually grow into a large, consequential value.</p> <p>Henri Poincaré, an esteemed physicist and mathematician, iterated a similar notion in his book <em>“Science and Method”</em> where he also gave examples of other unstable systems to explain how prediction becomes impossible because of our imperfect understanding of initial conditions and the presence of chaos.</p> <h2 id="modern-weather-forecasting">Modern Weather Forecasting</h2> <p>However, the presence of chaos does not mean meteorologists today are doing mere guesswork with their predictions. <strong>Predicting weather patterns a few days in advance is still feasible</strong> with modern science and technology.</p> <h3 id="ensemble-forecasting">Ensemble Forecasting</h3> <p>To reduce forecast errors, meteorologists employ techniques like <strong>ensemble forecasting</strong>. A set of slightly different initial conditions are fed into the model, and a range or “ensemble” of possible forecasts is produced to account for the uncertainties and the butterfly effect.</p> <p>The forecasts, which might look similar in the first few days but will eventually deviate from one another, can be interpreted in multiple ways:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Mean Forecast</strong>: Individual forecasts can be averaged out—this approach works fine when most individual forecasts favor a particular outcome but not when individual forecasts point toward very different possibilities.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Probabilistic Forecast</strong>: In cases where forecasts diverge significantly, meteorologists might prefer an ensemble forecasting model that computes the probabilities of various forecasts instead of trying to pinpoint an exact outcome.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p><strong>Deterministic systems</strong> are dynamical (time-variant) systems for which we can determine future states using our knowledge of the initial state and the evolution rule of the system. However, because of flaws or incompleteness in the evolution rule and inevitable uncertainties in our initial conditions—which grow into significant errors over time due to the butterfly effect—our ability to predict future states for unstable/chaotic systems is greatly reduced.</p> <p>Despite such limitations, various techniques can be implemented to make predictions with reasonable accuracy over shorter time frames. Thus, even though perfect predictions arbitrarily far into the future are impossible for certain deterministic systems, it is still possible for us to extend the time frame for which we can predict the future state with reasonable accuracy via improvements in:</p> <ul> <li>The precision of our measurements</li> <li>The evolution rule</li> <li>The model in general</li> </ul> <p>The interplay between determinism and unpredictability reveals one of the most fascinating aspects of our universe: that even when we understand the rules perfectly, the complexity of reality can still surprise us.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ul> <li>Laplace, Pierre-Simon. <em>A Philosophical Essay on Probabilities</em>. John Wiley &amp; Son, Chapman &amp; Hall.</li> <li>Lewin, Walter. <em>For the Love of Physics</em>. Free Press, 2012.</li> <li>Lorenz, Edward. <em>The Essence of Chaos</em>. University of Washington Press, 1995.</li> <li>Nykamp, DQ. “The stability of equilibria for discrete dynamical systems.” <em>Math Insight</em>. http://mathinsight.org/equilibria_discrete_dynamical_systems_stability</li> <li>Poincaré, Henri. “Chance.” In <em>Science and Method</em>, 1908.</li> <li>“What is an ensemble forecast?” <em>Met Office</em>. https://www.metoffice.gov.uk/research/weather/ensemble-forecasting/what-is-an-ensemble-forecast</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematical-modeling"/><category term="determinism"/><category term="chaos-theory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We try to understand what deterministic systems are, why their future can still be unpredictable, and whether being deterministic really means the future is knowable.]]></summary></entry></feed>